Okay, if you can hear me clap once, if you can hear me clap twice, thank you, Lisa,
for showing me that that actually works.
Okay, cool.
This is CS168, so hello, thank you for showing up at such a late time, it is the only time
we could get, so we'll have to live with it better than 8 a.m., in my opinion, okay.
Okay, so here's the outline for today, we'll start with like 5 minutes of logistics,
and then we will design the basic framework of the internet together for the rest of the lecture.
Okay, so all the logistics are already on the website, so I'm not going to read the website
out loud for you, but if you have any logistics questions, they are going to be answered on
these websites, I promise you, but since we're here, I'll just give you a couple of quick
reminders that are basically copy pasted from those two pages.
So if you do not have access to ed, or b-courses, or grade scope, or whatever,
please don't email us, you will be automatically added within a couple of days,
so just be patient, we will add you.
Discussions and office hours start next week, January 27th, we don't take attendance,
so attend whatever section you want.
The exam dates are on the website, there's one alternate exam in person only immediately
after the main exam, and if you're registered with DSP, the Disabled Students Program,
please send us your letter of accommodations as soon as possible so we can get that processed,
and just so we're all aware, your wellbeing is more important than this class, you do not have to
spend 20 all-nighters on this class, so if you need more time, there is a form on the website
for extensions.
Those are all the reminders I have for you.
Any questions on them?
Okay, here's our staff, I made this slide like five minutes ago, so let's hope it's correct,
but that's our staff.
Does anyone here want to say hi, wave to the crowd?
Okay, okay, great, so with logistics out of the way, we can now start building the internet,
talking about why it's interesting, why we should study it, and what it actually looks like.
So, I don't think I have to tell you what the internet is, it's this thing that transfers
data between computers, and all sorts of devices nowadays are connected to the internet, so not
just computers and phones, but cars, pacemakers, basically everything is connected to the internet.
So, one thing we should make clear right off the bat is that we're actually going to be studying
the infrastructure that we use to build the internet, and less about the things that people
build on top of the internet.
This will also probably make more sense once we talk about the layers of the internet today,
but as a running analogy throughout all of today and basically the whole class,
I think the internet system shares a lot of similarities with the postal system.
Remember that thing?
That's the thing you use to send mail to your friends.
So, we're going to use the postal system as a running analogy all day,
and here I can already use the analogy to say when we think about building the postal system,
I care about things like the mailbox, and the mailman, and the trucks that send mail.
So, I care about the infrastructure on which we are sending mail,
and for this class, we're not really going to focus on the mail that people are sending.
So, I don't really care if you're sending love letters or hate mail.
That's not really my concern.
What we really care about is the infrastructure that we have to build,
so that application developers can build whatever they want on top of the internet.
So, that's kind of where our focus is for this class.
Okay, so why should we study the internet?
Well, again, I don't think I have to convince you that the internet is basically everywhere.
It affects businesses.
It affects the way we talk to each other.
It affects the way we learn.
It affects politics.
It affects health and diseases.
So, internet is everywhere.
Okay, enough said about that.
So, what makes the internet interesting?
Like, why is there a whole separate class for the internet,
as opposed to just studying it in, I don't know, CS61B or something?
Well, it turns out the internet is actually kind of a special field
compared to all the other computer science fields.
So, here are some questions that if I went to other computer scientists
and I asked them about the internet, these are the things that they would say to me.
So, if I go to some hardcore theory person, like a CS70 or CS170 person,
and I presented to them the internet, they would say, this makes no sense.
You have not proven anything about the internet.
There's no formal model.
You haven't written any proofs.
So, what are you doing?
There's no proof.
So, from a theorist's perspective, the internet makes no sense.
There is no model of it.
There's no proof that it works.
It just works.
By contrast, if I take networking and the internet,
and I present it to hardware engineers, so like the EE side,
and I show them the internet and how it works,
they will also be confused and they'll say, what are you doing?
You don't have any benchmarks for what constitutes good performance.
So, in the hardware space, there's all these different metrics.
So, for example, when someone's building a chip,
the chip has all these performance benchmarks,
and we say the chip is good because it runs at this performance,
and the chip is bad because it runs at this performance.
So, hardware engineers, they have a measure of what makes something good or bad.
But in the internet, not so much.
There isn't really a benchmark that says, this is where the internet is good.
So, if you go to hardware engineers, they'll also be confused and they'll say,
what's going on?
How do you build the internet when there's no standard
for what makes the internet good?
So, these are all questions that make the internet a unique design challenge.
So, we have to tackle these throughout this class.
Maybe a different one is, if you go to your parents,
or if I go to my parents and I tell them, oh, I'm studying the internet,
they'll be like, what are you talking about?
It already works.
I go on Facebook all the time, and I can see cat videos.
So, what are you studying?
So, turns out, we're also going to look at what's on the cutting edge of the internet
and why we still have to continue building and developing new things.
So, while the internet seems like it works from the perspective of, say, my parents,
well, there are still things that need to be studied,
and we'll take a look at those throughout the course.
So, these are just some reasons why I think the internet is interesting and special
compared to some of the other topics you might have studied so far.
Okay.
So, let me run you through a couple of things that make designing the internet hard.
So, this is, again, things that make the internet a unique design challenge
that you might not have to wrangle with if you're designing something else,
like you're building, I don't know, a new computer, or you're building a chip.
These are things that you probably didn't have to deal with,
but with the internet, these are challenges that we care about, and they're special.
So, here's one.
The internet is federated.
So, I don't know about you, but there's no such thing as, like, internet incorporated.
There's no company that runs the entire internet.
In fact, the internet is actually made up of hundreds of thousands of different organizations,
companies, governments, that all have to work together to form the internet.
There's no single company.
So, AT&T is a company that works in the internet space.
China Telecom is a company that works in the internet space.
Verizon, UC Berkeley itself has people working on the internet.
Verizon，UC
So, all these people from all these different companies have to work together to build the internet,
and that's a challenge that a lot of other design fields don't have to deal with,
or computer science fields, I guess.
So, everyone has to cooperate in order for the internet to work on a global scale.
And so, this already introduces something interesting.
There are actually business incentives to the internet.
So, these companies, they want to make money, and that means that they're competing with each other.
And that means that, for example, even though AT&T and Verizon have to work together to give
internet connectivity to all of the US, AT&T and Verizon probably don't want to share
private information with each other.
They don't want to share their business secrets, because that would be bad.
So, already we see that this is something that you probably haven't had to think about
when you're, I don't know, programming something for your class.
You don't have to think about, what about my competitors?
What are they going to do?
But in the internet, we do care about business incentives,
and that'll be a big part of something that we'll see later called BGP.
So, another challenge is the internet being federated, that is,
being made up of all these different operators, it also makes innovation hard.
So, if you think about any other field, like, I don't know, computers or phones or whatever,
if someone invents a new feature, that's great.
Like Apple just invented this brand new feature on their iPhone,
and so they're going to keep it secret.
They're not going to share it with anyone else, and now they can sell their phones
and beat everyone else because they have a brand new feature.
But in the internet, it's not so easy, because remember, the way that the internet works
is all of these operators have to work together to form the internet.
So, if you have a brand new feature, but none of your competitors implement the feature,
it's useless.
The whole point is that everyone has to run on the same infrastructure
and use the same protocols.
So, here's a case where already, it seems like the incentive to make something new,
it's kind of weird.
It's not like I can make something new and then sell it to the world
and hide it from my rivals.
If I make something new, I actually have to make sure other people support it too,
because we all are working together to form the internet.
It's not a single company.
So, already there's all these different incentives, and it makes it harder to innovate.
These are all things that we're going to see as obstacles or things to design around.
So, it's kind of cool.
Okay, what else is interesting about the internet?
It's scale-level, so hopefully I don't have to convince you the internet is very big
and it is constantly growing bigger.
The number of users just keeps increasing.
The number of things we put on the internet, the things that we send over the internet,
is also constantly increasing.
And the internet has to be able to handle tremendous scale,
scale that basically no other piece of software has to handle.
The internet is also evolving.
So, again, because people keep asking for more applications, different things,
the internet has to continually evolve.
So, for example, they invented email, and now the internet has to support email,
and then video streaming became a thing.
Now we have to support video streaming, and then AI became a thing,
and now we have to support AI training and so forth.
So, the internet itself is also constantly evolving based on what users want.
Something else about the internet that makes it hard is that it's diverse.
So, some users, or all users are different basically.
So, some users use a lot of data.
Some users don't use any data at all.
Some users are nice.
Some users are malicious.
So, everyone is a little bit different in what they want and what they need.
Same thing on, for example, the company side.
Some companies are serving video.
Some companies are serving emails.
So, everyone wants a slightly different thing out of the internet,
and we have to somehow be able to support all these different devices, users, services,
each of which has their own special requests.
So, it's a really daunting challenge to try and service everyone's requests,
but it's something we're going to try to design.
Okay, here's one that, again,
maybe you haven't seen before when you're programming other things,
but the internet is asynchronous.
And what I mean by that is that the internet is all over the world.
So, it's not the case that when you update something,
someone else gets the update right away.
There's a speed limit in physics called the speed of light.
Things cannot travel faster than the speed of light.
So, what that means is, for example, if I update something here in San Francisco,
well, then by the time it reaches New York,
even if it travels at the fastest possible speed with no obstacles along the way,
it would still take 13 milliseconds.
13 milliseconds is actually a really long time in computer world,
and if you have a CPU that runs at this particular frequency,
that means that your CPU has already executed 42 million instructions
by the time your message has reached New York.
And you can imagine, if they send a message back to you,
that's another 42 million cycles.
So, by the time you get the information,
you have already done lots of other work,
and the information that you receive is, by definition, outdated.
There's just no way to get instant updates from New York,
because it's too far away.
So, because the internet is built in all these different places,
things that you send over the internet,
they're going to be outdated, and we have to deal with that.
There's no way to instantly update someone on the other side of the country or the world.
Okay, a couple more challenges, and then I'll take questions.
So, one challenge is, the internet has to handle failures.
It would be really bad if a server somewhere went down,
and the entire world just stopped working.
There's no more internet.
So, we have to build the internet in such a way that if something fails,
like a server goes down, or a router goes down, or something,
or there's a power outage in Berkeley,
the rest of the world should still be able to service the internet,
or access the internet.
So, we have to handle failures, and we have to handle it at scale.
So, for example, even if a whole city has a blackout,
the internet should still continue working for everyone else in the world.
So, wires could break, network devices could break,
a city could go down in terms of blackout,
and the internet should still work.
And even weirder compounding this issue
is that when something fails, you might not know right away.
Remember the issue from before, where everyone is located far away?
By the time you find out that something has failed,
that news might be old.
Who knows? They might be back up.
That news might be outdated.
So, combining this and the fact that information that you get is outdated,
it makes things really tricky.
And in fact, some say that the internet was the first system
that really had to handle failures at this kind of amazing worldwide scale.
So, when you're writing a program and it crashes, it's no big deal.
But when the internet, when people are writing the internet,
we got to make sure this thing does not crash,
has to work for basically all of time, which is pretty big challenge.
So, I mean, here's just an example.
If I have 50 links, and we'll talk about links next time,
and if they all work 99% of the time,
there's already a 39% chance that something fails.
So, if I expand this to the entire world,
things are failing all the time.
There's like millions of wires in the world.
Right now, as we're speaking, something is failing,
but the internet is still working.
How do they build that?
That's something we're going to find out.
Okay, so to recap all the things we just saw.
Why is the internet interesting?
Why are we studying this as opposed to studying anything else?
It's federated.
Lots of different companies make it up.
The scale is amazing.
It's constantly evolving.
The users want all sorts of different things that we have to service.
Everything is asynchronous when you receive something.
It's outdated already, and we have to handle failures at scale.
We can't let a single service going down break the entire internet.
So, all of these are things that are going to come back and haunt us
as we try and design things,
but it will also lead to some pretty beautiful and creative solutions.
So, I think it's kind of cool.
Okay, sorry, just a couple more slides.
So, designing the internet required new ways of thinking.
So, when the internet was designed,
a lot of the things that we're about to see,
they didn't actually exist yet.
So, people had to think in new ways
to understand how to build things that are fault tolerant
and work at big scale and asynchronous
and all the things that we talked about.
So, when the internet was designed,
it also introduced all sorts of different ways of thinking,
which is kind of interesting.
And nowadays, all sorts of modern systems,
like cloud services, cloud computing, AI training, whatever,
all of these other fields have actually started
to learn lessons from the internet.
So, the internet was the first system that learned
how to do things like handle failures at scale,
but as a result, the lessons that people learn
when they built the internet have now spread
to all these other things, like distributed computing
or AI training or cloud computing.
So, that's kind of interesting,
that the things you learn are also applicable
in lots of other fields.
So, as mentioned before, some of the ways of thinking
that were pioneered by the internet
and now used all over the place,
we already saw earlier, there is no theoretical model,
there's no benchmark, there is no target you can hit
or way that you can prove that things are working.
So, there actually is no sense
in which the internet is optimal.
It's not the best solution,
and who knows what the best solution is, I have no idea,
but it balances lots of different goals very well.
So, we say it works well, even though I cannot prove to you
that it's the best or that it hits any particular benchmark.
And also, as mentioned, just because your code works
doesn't mean it's good enough for the internet.
You write a new internet protocol, send it out,
it's not good enough.
We have to make sure that we respect
companies' business incentives, for example,
that rivals don't share information,
and our code has to run at huge scale
and handle fault tolerance and be receptive to failures.
So, not only does code have to work,
but it has to respond to all these challenges.
Nowadays, when people write code for other applications,
they also think about these things, which is pretty cool.
Okay, I will pause for questions.
Okay, great.
So, what are we going to design in this class?
So, we're going to be spending basically the whole class
designing tons of protocols.
What are protocols?
Protocols are basically a set of rules
for how two people communicate.
And since the internet is all about
having people across the world communicate,
well, then stands to the reason that most of the internet
is basically built of lots of protocols.
So, we're going to build lots of protocols for communication,
and with them, we'll get the internet.
So, what is a protocol?
It's a set of rules on how two people communicate,
and you can split it into two things.
So, a protocol consists of syntax and semantics.
So, what are these things?
Well, syntax tells me what does the message mean?
So, when someone hands me a big pile of zeros and ones,
what are they talking about?
What does the zero mean?
What does the one mean?
How do I decode this to get useful, meaningful messages?
That's what the syntax is.
And then the semantics say, when I get a message,
what do I do?
So, if someone tells me resend,
okay, great, what does that mean?
Does it mean I should resend now?
Does it mean I resend later?
What does that mean?
So, we have to figure out what the messages mean,
and also, what do I do in response to those messages?
Put those two things together,
you get a protocol.
So, to give you an example,
what's your protocol for asking a question?
Well, you should raise your hand,
and we both know what that means.
I know it means you have a question.
You know it means you have a question.
So, we both agree on the syntax.
That putting your hand up is syntax for I have a question.
And then what do you do when you raise your hand?
You don't just start blabbing.
You wait for someone to acknowledge you and say,
oh, you have a question.
And then you can start talking and ask your question.
And if, for some reason, we don't see you,
maybe you'll wave your hand more.
You say, excuse me, or something like that.
But these are all rules that I agree on, you agree on,
and that's how we communicate.
It's by using this protocol.
And it turns out designing protocols
is what we're going to be doing basically the whole semester.
And it's actually not as easy as it seems.
There's actually whole organizations whose entire job
is just to debate protocols all day.
So, if that sounds fun, you can go join the IETF,
Internet Engineering Task Force.
And basically their entire job is just
to make protocols, standardize them
so that everyone knows how it works, and then publish them.
So, if you ever see RFCs, those are documents
that just contain the protocol.
And everyone talks about it and argues about it.
And if everyone thinks it's good,
then it becomes a new internet protocol.
So, this is what we're going to be doing
for basically all of this semester.
Questions, thoughts, okay?
Great, so now that we know what the internet is,
why it's interesting, we can actually start building it.
We're going to build it today,
because today's the only day anyone's coming to lecture.
I know it's 6.30, so we're going to build it today.
Okay, so let's do it.
So, I'm going to start with the most basic building block,
and I'm going to slowly work my way up
to something that's going to connect the entire world.
And along the way,
I'll use the postal analogy,
because I think it bears a lot of similarities to the internet.
So, the first thing I need,
if I want to allow people to communicate,
I need some way to move data from point A to point B.
That's the most basic thing I could possibly ask for.
Some technology that takes data at point A
and moves it to point B.
And this could be anything you want.
So, in the postal analogy, this could be a mailman
walking on the streets and carrying your letters
from point A to point B.
It could be the pony express.
Like, you put the bag of mail on the rider,
they get on the horse,
and they ride across the wild west to deliver your mail.
It could be a carrier pigeon.
Like, you tie the mail to the pigeon,
and the pigeon flies off.
And apparently, according to Wikipedia,
if you give a pigeon a big flash drive
with like 500 gigabytes,
the pigeon might be faster than the internet.
So, food for thought.
Not important, but something funny I found.
Okay, so these are all things that can carry data through space.
And this is our most fundamental building block.
So, in the same way that pigeons or mailman
can carry data across space,
well, there's also physical ways to do that
in the electrical engineering world.
So, we won't really spend a lot of time in this class
on how you move bits across space.
This is more of a low-level thing.
I think it's a little bit of a challenge
I think EE-122 is the class you take
if you're interested in this.
But, basically, you can imagine
there are these physical things
that let you transfer data across space.
For example, a wire.
I am connected to like 20 wires up here.
These wires are carrying data across space.
Or, for example, if you have an optical fiber,
you can flash light signals,
and that would also send data
to the other side of the optical fiber.
Or you could use wireless radio waves,
like you broadcast a radio signal,
and other people get it.
But the bottom line is,
these are some forms of physical processes
that allow you to take data from point A
and move it to point B.
That's all I care about.
It's a building block.
It works.
So, I'm good.
Okay.
So, with this building block,
what can I now do?
I have this great building block
and move data across space,
but just having a mailman
doesn't count as a postal system.
So, the next step is,
I'm gonna use the first building block
to build something else.
That's a really fundamental idea
that we'll see over and over again today.
Using the first building block,
I'm gonna build something more complicated
and more sophisticated.
So, my first building block was physical stuff
that moves data across space.
With that idea,
I can take everyone in a local area,
for example, UC Berkeley,
or a town, or my house,
and I can connect up everyone in that local area.
So, for example, I have these four circles
representing four computers
in some close by space,
and I can just take a wire, for example,
and I can just hook them all up to the same wire.
Now, they are all connected together,
and they can send messages to each other.
So, we call this a link,
because it's connecting up multiple machines,
and if I use links,
I can connect up everyone in a local area.
For example, I could take some wires,
I could connect all of us in here to the same wire,
and then we would all be connected on a particular link.
And what's great about a link is,
now we can exchange data,
and people have a fancy term for data,
they call it packets,
but all that is, is it's a bunch of ones and zeros
representing something you wanna send.
It could be a picture,
it could be a video,
it could be an email,
or whatever it is,
you encode it in a packet,
and you send it on the link.
So, we built something interesting.
We used our first technology, single wire.
We connected a bunch of people,
now we have a way to exchange data between people.
Okay, but there is a problem,
which is, I stopped at this step right here.
How is this going to scale up?
How can I possibly take a wire
and connect every single person in the world?
Or how do I take an optical fiber
and connect that to every single person in the world?
I can't.
So, instead, I have to think about,
how do I connect people across further distances?
Let's say, for example, I have two towns,
here's a town, it's got four people in it,
they're all happily connected with the link,
and then here's another town with four people
also happily connected with the link.
How do I connect these two towns together?
Say, someone from here
wants to send a message to someone from here,
how do they communicate?
So, I mean, something you could try
is you could try to link up everyone
with a bunch of links.
So, go install a bunch of wires between people,
between every pair of houses,
or every pair of nodes,
but hopefully you can already see
this is going to get very complicated,
very expensive, very quickly,
so we don't want to do this.
So, instead, I'm going to go borrow
from my postal analogy
and bring in something else called a post office.
Have people even been to post offices?
Because you're also young, I don't know.
But a post office is a building,
you can go there and drop off your mail
and they will deliver the mail
to its destination for you.
So, here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to introduce a post office
in the first town
and introduce a post office in the second town.
And instead of doing the thing from earlier
where I draw wires between every single pair of computers,
I'm just going to connect the two post offices.
So, for example, drop a wire between them
or in the postal analogy,
tell the mailman to go between these two buildings.
And so, what's great about this is now,
for example, if this person wants to talk to this person,
instead of directly sending a message
because we already saw that can't scale,
you can send a message to your post office
and then what's your post office going to do?
It's going to forward the message.
So, pass it along this link to the other post office
and then that post office looks at the letter and says,
oh, it's for this person.
Let me drop it off for that person
at their final destination.
So, by using this post office approach,
I only needed a single extra link
and now both of these towns are connected.
Which is great.
Thoughts on how I built this?
Okay, that's great.
I connected two towns.
If I've connected two towns,
what is stopping me from connecting three or four
or all of them?
And in fact, that's what we do.
So, we're going to go crazy
and we're going to connect all the towns
with all sorts of post offices and houses.
So, you can imagine this is like a map of the world.
I have all these different houses lying around
and all these different towns.
There's all these different post offices connecting them.
And if I connect everyone up together
in the whole wide world,
I get the internet.
And I built it in a way
where I took small building blocks
and worked my way up something like this.
And if you squint at this a little bit,
you'll see why we call the internet
a network of networks.
That's a term that people like to use.
So, what does that mean?
Well, if you stare at this,
we have all these little towns
and each little town is kind of doing its own thing.
So, here's a network.
Here's a network.
Each little town is doing its own little thing.
And then all the towns connect to each other
to form the internet.
So, why do we call this a network of networks?
It's because all of these little individual pieces
form a network.
And then we connect all the subnetworks up
into a big, gigantic network.
That's the internet.
That's your first peek of the internet.
It's this little crappy picture on the slide.
That's the internet.
Kind of.
Okay.
Pause for questions.
Great.
So, to break down this diagram a little bit more
and to introduce some more terminology,
it's the first lecture.
There's a lot of terminology.
Sorry.
But if you look at this picture,
we're not going to stop saying post offices and houses
because the internet is not actually post offices and houses,
but in fact, the internet is end hosts and routers.
Those are the fancy words that we're going to use.
So, in this class, when I draw an end host, I draw a circle.
I tried my best to make this always true,
maybe some exceptions,
but 99% of the time when you see a circle in this class,
the circle is the end host.
These are the machines that want to communicate
over the internet.
So, as an analogy, these are the houses.
People live in the houses
and they want to talk to each other.
In the internet world, the end hosts are, for example,
your laptop is an end host,
your phone is an end host,
Google server that answers your search queries,
that's an end host.
These are the people that want to talk to each other
and have things to say.
By contrast, these switches,
they're like the post offices.
So, the post office, it's not really there to talk to you.
I don't know about you,
but like I'm not talking to my post office,
but the post office exists to forward packets
toward their destination.
So, the post office, its entire job for existing
is to receive a packet and say,
okay, this packet is supposed to go that way.
So, I'll send it that way,
or this packet is supposed to go that way.
So, I'll send it that way.
So, the router, its entire job in life
is to sit there, receive your packets,
and forward them to other post offices or hosts
so that they get closer to their destination.
So, sometimes we'll call them routers,
sometimes we'll call them switches.
For the purpose of this class,
they are basically the same.
Near the end, I'll tell you why there's two names for them,
but for now, pretend they're the same thing.
So, we have end hosts, we have switches, aka routers.
Okay, great.
So, as mentioned, when we built this thing,
we built it in layers.
I didn't call it out yet,
but we actually built it in three separate layers.
And what's great about this is we've created for ourselves
layers of abstraction.
We love layers of abstraction.
Hopefully, you've seen them in all the prerequisite classes,
61A, 61B.
61A，61B。
Hopefully, you're sick of them at this point,
but layers of abstraction are wonderful.
Layers of abstraction are why,
when I'm programming on my computer,
or when I'm using my computer to browse the web,
I don't care about the voltage levels in my computer.
I'm not thinking about that.
Or when I drive a car, I'm not thinking about,
oh, how is the fuel getting to the fuel tank?
I don't care about that.
I just have to turn the steering wheel
and the car goes the direction I want.
So layers of abstraction are great.
They allow me to hide lower level details that I don't need.
And when we built the internet,
we also built it with layers of abstraction.
So if you're someone working hard at layer three,
that is your job is to connect up the local networks
to form the internet.
For example, you're laying an undersea cable
from like America to Europe.
You don't care about all the things happening beneath.
You don't care about the voltage levels
that move bits across space on the wires.
You don't care about how the local networks are linked up.
You just care about building things at your layer,
which is connecting up the local networks.
Maybe another way of putting it is,
if you're the person building this link,
you don't care what's happening inside this bubble, this town.
You also don't care about what's happening in this town.
You just have to drop this link.
That's your job.
Or for example, if you're the person linking up hosts
with links in a local network,
you don't care about the voltage levels in the wire.
All you have to do is you say,
there's this magical device that connects point A and point B.
I'll use this to wire up a bunch of people.
I have a network.
How the bits are moving across space?
Is it optical?
Is it electrical?
Not my concern.
So abstraction is really great.
It allows us to innovate at these different layers separately.
We can have different teams,
different researchers working at different layers,
and they don't have to worry about
what's happening at the other layers.
I can just assume that I'm given services from my lower layers
that I can rely on,
and I provide services to the layer above me that they can use.
So this is great.
We want to build the internet like this
because it gives us modularity.
And that's a key idea that you'll see over and over again.
Okay, as mentioned before,
because of the way we built the internet,
that is we use lots of post offices
and connected everyone in the network of networks,
what that means is that packets don't always
directly reach their destination.
So for example, if this person wants to talk to this person,
it is not the case that there is a direct wire connecting them.
I don't know about you,
like there's no wire coming out of my computer
that like goes all the way to Asia.
I don't think I have a wire like that.
So instead,
if I want to send a packet somewhere else around the world,
I have to forward the packet across multiple routers.
And in the analogy,
this is like going between multiple post offices.
So I send the packet to my local post office,
they send it to the post office next door,
and then they put the mail like on a boat
and the boat travels across the sea,
goes to this post office,
they forward it,
crosses another sea,
and then it goes to another post office.
And only after all the hopping and hopping
does it actually reach its final destination.
So packets can take multiple hops is the term that we use
before they can reach their destination.
And that's fine.
That's just something we're going to use in our design,
but that's how it's built.
Okay.
Also, because of the way that we built this,
because we built it using layers,
we don't actually have to use the same technology
at each of these,
on each of these links.
So for example,
these links,
they could be wired,
like there's a wire connecting me to this post office.
Maybe this link is optical.
That's a different technology.
That's okay.
The packet just travels across this link
using a different technology.
That's okay.
And then maybe this link is wireless,
like it's using radio waves.
And then maybe this link is wired again.
And these links are optical.
That's totally fine.
Everyone can use their own link level technology.
And the packet still reaches its destination.
So this is wonderful.
This allows different networks
to use the technology that's best for them.
So maybe this network decided,
I want to use wireless,
but this one thinks I want to use optical.
It's totally fine.
They can do that.
And everything works out nicely.
So this is great.
And it's because of the layers of abstraction
that we got this to work.
It's because at layer three,
we don't care what's going on below.
Okay.
So one more property of layer three
that we should talk about.
And if you're wondering why it's like this,
we'll talk about why next time.
Today is more about how it's built.
Next time is why we built it this way.
But layer three service model
is something we call best effort.
Best effort basically means I will try,
but if I don't succeed, it sucks to be you.
I'm not going to promise that it's going to work.
So what this means is a couple of things.
One, it means that packets are limited in size.
That's not really best effort,
but I couldn't fit it anywhere else.
But just be aware that packets can't be infinitely large.
There's limit to them.
Now you know.
But here's the part that is best effort.
So packets can get lost.
For example, I don't know,
this post office gets confused
and sends it the wrong way.
Packet gets lost, doesn't reach its destination.
Packets could get reordered.
Like I send two packets, part one and part two,
and part two gets there before part one.
That could happen.
Packets could get corrupted.
The data inside could actually become incorrect
as it travels across the network.
So all of these are failures
that can happen on the network.
And what the network is basically telling you is,
I will try to get your packet toward its destination,
but I'm not going to promise.
If I fail, it sucks to be you.
I'm not going to fix it for you.
And in fact, the network won't even tell you if it fails.
So you won't even get an error message
saying that the delivery failed.
You just have to deal with the failure yourself.
So that's the best effort service model
and that is what the network provides.
And again, if you think this is weird
and you want to pick a different service model,
you come back next time.
We'll talk about why it was designed this way.
But basically the punchline here is,
we can't stop at layer three.
If we stop at layer three,
every piece of data you ever send or receive
is best effort.
You send it, it doesn't get there.
Sorry, nothing I can do about it.
If you care about things actually reaching their destination
with a guarantee on them, we have to build more layers.
So we're going to build more layers.
Unless you have questions before I build more,
but we're done with one, two, three for now.
And we're going to go further up.
Question.
That's a great question.
How does the router know where the destination is?
Like, do I forward it that way or that way?
It's going to take me six lectures to answer that question.
So come back, I don't know, in a couple of weeks.
We're going to spend six lectures answering that.
But it's a great question.
Okay, there's a whole topic called routing
that's going to solve that.
Any other great questions?
Okay, great.
So we finished building layers one, two, three.
We're now going to build four through seven.
There's a new layer that we're going to build.
And remember, the reason why we're building this layer
is because if we stopped at layer three, it's true.
We get global connectivity.
I can send packets anywhere in the world,
but there's no guarantee that they actually arrive,
which I don't like.
I want packets to actually get there.
So to make sure that packets actually reach their destination,
I introduce a layer four.
Layer four builds on top of layer three,
which means I can use the services provided by layer three.
That is global connectivity.
But I'm now going to add extra features
to make sure that packets actually get there.
For example, if a packet gets lost,
I'm going to send it again and send it again
and send it again until it gets there.
If a packet arrives out of order,
I'm going to reassemble them in the correct order.
If the user wants to send a big piece of data,
I'll split the data up and then reassemble it
into the form that the user wants.
So all of these features and more happen at layer four,
which we call transport.
And this allows us to reliably deliver packets.
And when we transition from layer three to four,
I think there's also a little bit of a change in the mindset
in which we think about things.
These are not official terms,
but what I think about when I think about layers one, two, three
is I think about like a packet mindset.
And what that means is each piece of data,
it's a packet and that packet is independent.
So the internet is just all these packets flying around independently.
There's nothing that connects one packet to the other.
They're all just separate packets flying across the internet.
But once I get to layer four,
I can stop thinking in terms of packets,
which is just pieces of data flying around the internet.
I can start thinking instead in terms of flows or connections.
And what that means is this is actually a stream
of related packets being exchanged between two people.
So oftentimes when you want to talk to someone,
you're talking to someone for a long time.
We have a conversation or I'm downloading a video from YouTube.
Well, in that case, I am talking to YouTube for a very long time.
And so we're going to be exchanging lots of related packets.
Like here's the first part of your video.
Here's the next part of your video.
Here's the next part of your video and so forth.
So once you get to layer four,
we stop thinking in terms of individual packets
floating across the internet.
And we start thinking in terms of flows,
a bunch of related packets streaming back and forth
between a sender and a receiver, a client and a server,
point A and point B, basically two people.
So once you get to layer four and above,
we can start thinking in a slightly different mindset.
And we'll think in both of these mindsets
plenty throughout the semester.
So it's okay if you don't totally see the difference yet,
but something I wanted to call out early.
Okay, so we have a final layer.
By the way, if you're annoyed by the counting here,
it's because five and six are obsolete.
This model was developed in like the 1970s
and five and six are no longer used.
So instead we have to skip from four to seven.
Everyone does it.
We'll deal with it.
But basically the idea is that now you have layer four
and that unlocks the ability for users to build
whatever applications they want on top of layer four.
So for example, you're building YouTube.
You want to give videos to the user?
That's great.
You can use the transport layer to form connections
and send videos to users.
What if instead, I don't want to build a video service.
I want to build a gaming service
or I want to build the game that runs online.
That's great.
In that case, your application is a game
and it still runs on top of layer four.
It sends data back and forth between users.
Or you could build email.
Okay, that's great.
You build email, it still runs on top of layer four.
So what's great about this layering abstraction
or this layering structure
is that once we have these four layers,
users can build whatever the heck they want
on top of the four layers.
They get reliable connectivity
which relies on global connectivity
which relies on individual links
which relies on physical data floating across space.
But as the programmer, you don't care about any of this stuff.
You can just build on top of it
and say, I want to build gaming application.
Okay, great, build it.
And you can build it on top of the internet.
So when users are building things using the internet,
they're building up here at layer seven.
And that's something we'll look at too.
Those are the five layers that we care about.
There's going to be little asterisks
and little additions throughout the semester.
But that's kind of the general model that we use.
I guess I should also mention at this point,
I don't think I called it out anywhere else,
that this is not a perfect picture.
So it's not always going to be the case
that something cleanly slots into a given layer.
So there are protocols that span different layers.
There are protocols that kind of live between layers.
So this is a nice conceptual picture,
but just want to call out it's not the case
that everything fits cleanly in these layers.
This is more of a design principle that we use
to make things look good.
But in real life, the picture is a little bit messier.
But this is kind of what it looks like.
Okay, thoughts, questions.
Do you want like a one minute break?
I know it's late at night.
So it's dead silent.
I can't tell if that's a yes or no.
You want a one minute break?
You want me to just plow on and finish this thing?
I'll give you like one minute.
Okay, enjoy and then we'll finish.
All right, I can take Zoom questions while I'm waiting.
All right, this is Zoom questions I've been answered.
Thanks.
For the layers one, I think five is session and six is presentation.
And they had to do with like how the application looks.
But beyond that, I truly don't know anything
about those two layers.
Sorry.
These are all good questions though.
Okay, is everyone ready to keep going?
Five, four, three, two, one.
Okay, time to keep going.
So there's just one more topic for today
and we are all out of here.
Okay, so let's think about what we've built so far.
We've built something that gives you global connectivity
using all these different layers.
And remember that when you send data, you send it in a packet.
That's a bunch of ones and zeros representing the data you want to send.
And the packet travels across multiple hops
until it reaches its destination.
But there's just one problem.
If I take all these ones and zeros
and I just deliver them to my post office,
this post office has no idea what you're talking about.
What are these ones and zeros?
What am I supposed to do with them?
It's like if I go to my post office
and I just hand them a box, okay, great.
What do I do with the box?
So we actually have to add some extra information
which we'll call metadata.
And that's going to tell us what to do with the box.
So in the analogy, you cannot go to the post office
and just give them a piece of paper and say,
here you go, you have to put the piece of paper
in an envelope.
And on the envelope, you have to write information about
where do you want this letter to go?
Who is sending the letter?
Things like that.
So instead of just sending a bunch of ones and zeros
that correspond to my data,
I need to put extra information on top
that tells the routers what to do with the letter
so that they can take my letter or my packet
and deliver it to its correct destination.
So this is the motivation for why we need headers.
So here's your very first header.
Headers can have all sorts of interesting data in them.
A lot of modern protocols,
we'll see protocols with like 10 things in the header.
But for today, let's just think about
the two simplest things you could possibly put in a header.
So one thing that the header clearly needs is,
we have to put where the packet is going.
If I don't put it's going to be,
these routers are simply going to have no idea
where this packet is supposed to go.
So I have to put in the header,
this packet is destined for B, that's required.
If you don't put this,
the routers have no idea where it's going.
Another useful header that's technically not required
but is basically always there
because it's useful is who's sending the packet.
So for example here,
I would say the packet is coming from A.
And this is useful for example,
if the recipient B wants to reply,
they can look at the letter or the envelope
or the header and say,
oh, this packet was from A,
I'm going to send a reply to A.
So while not required,
having the sender field is very useful,
especially if for example,
the recipient wants to send a reply.
So in basically all headers we'll see,
there's going to be a from field and a to field,
two things that are very useful in headers.
And so these are called the headers,
they're the metadata,
the thing you write on top of the envelope,
and the thing inside the actual data,
that's the payload.
Just a fancy way of saying,
that's the actual data you want to send.
These ones and zeros could represent an image,
a video, whatever you want.
Okay, something important about this header is,
it's not actually in English.
Like if I open up my computer,
it doesn't say from A to B,
that'd be nice,
but that's not what it says.
This is actually encoded in lots of ones and zeros as well.
And as we mentioned before,
when we design a protocol,
everyone has to agree on what the protocol looks like.
So what that means is for example,
when you design this protocol,
you might say, first eight bits,
tell me who the packet is from.
And the next eight bits,
tell me where the packet is going to,
things like that.
But everyone has to agree on this.
If you're using one format,
and I'm using a different format,
we don't speak the same language.
So when you send a packet,
I'm going to have no idea what your header is saying.
So when we design these headers,
they have to be designed in a standardized way,
and all computers,
my computer, your computer,
every other computer,
they all understand exactly
what these headers look like.
It's very important to make sure that
the packets make sense to everyone.
Okay, so those are what headers look like.
Now we know why they're needed.
And I'm going to draw you a picture of how headers
relate to the layers of abstraction
that we talk about.
So we'll combine these two topics together
to finish our kind of high level overview
of what the internet looks like.
So here's kind of another mail analogy picture.
So at the very bottom,
we have the mail room.
Those are the rooms that move mail from point A to point B.
And then maybe we have a secretary.
And then at the very top,
we have the boss, the CEO.
So let's say, here's Alice.
She's the CEO.
She wants to send a message to Bob,
who's also the CEO.
And she has this very ominous message.
I don't know why it's so ominous,
but they were in the oldest lights,
so I copied them over.
So Alice wants to say,
your days are numbered.
Very spooky.
And she wants to send this to Bob.
And remember,
the way that we built the layers of abstraction
is that I guess you'll see once we do the demo,
but the packet's actually going to travel down the stack
and then back up.
So let's see what that looks like.
So Alice is the CEO.
She's the boss.
She has no time for petty matters like sending mail.
So what's she going to do?
She's going to talk to her secretary and say,
secretary, I have mail that I want to send.
I am the rich CEO.
I'm going to make you send it for me.
So she takes her letter,
hands it off to the secretary,
and the secretary does the work of
putting that letter in the envelope
and attaching a header.
And the header says it's from Alice and it goes to Bob.
So the secretary did some extra work
and the secretary wrapped a header around the packet.
That's something that we're going to see.
So an extra header got attached
as Alice passed the letter down to the secretary.
And now the secretary says,
well, I'm the secretary,
but my job is in sending mail.
I'm not a mailman.
So I'm going to pass this downstairs one more time
to the mailroom.
And the mailroom is going to look at this envelope
and say, okay, well, this is from Alice's building
and it's going to Bob's building.
So I'm going to attach another header
and this header has Alice's street address
and Bob's street address.
And I'm going to attach this other header
and in the analogy,
you can think of this as putting the envelope in a box.
So now we have a letter wrapped in an envelope,
wrapped in a box, two layers of wrapping around it.
And now that we've reached the very bottom,
this box can go into a mail truck
or a mailman can carry it
all the way over to Bob's building.
So what happens at Bob's building?
Well, the mailroom opens up the box.
Though I got mail, I open up the box.
And so what happens is this outer most layer,
the box gets unwrapped, right?
I don't need this anymore.
It's already at four, five, six Bob's street.
It's reached Bob's building.
I don't need this outer header anymore.
So I'm going to unwrap it.
And when I unwrap it,
I expose this next header that says,
oh, it's going to Bob.
So I'm going to go ahead and give this to Bob's secretary.
So notice what happened here is that the box got unwrapped.
It reveals the inner header
and I pass the envelope up to the secretary.
And what does the secretary do?
What the secretary says, I got an envelope.
I'm going to open it and see what's inside.
So the secretary is going to unwrap another header,
specifically this blue one,
exposing the original message.
And then the secretary passes the letter up to Bob
and Bob gets the original message
with no extra headers attached.
So to play it one more time,
we started up here.
Alice had a message.
And as we went down the stack
from higher layers to lower layers,
more headers got wrapped around.
The secretary wrapped an envelope around the letter.
The mailman wrapped a box around the envelope.
Once we got to the bottom,
it was sent across the mail system to Bob's building.
And then Bob's building unwrapped the headers one by one
as the packet went upwards.
So I started here.
We lost the outer header.
It exposes the inner header,
pass it up to the secretary.
The secretary unwraps the envelope,
exposes the letter,
and then gives the letter to Bob.
So that's the pattern that we're going to see
over and over again.
The messages start at the very top.
They work their way down,
getting more layers added to them
and more headers added to them,
like an onion.
And then on the other side,
the onion gets unwrapped,
exposing the original message inside.
And this happens across all the layers.
Thoughts on the analogy so far?
Okay.
So that's the postal analogy.
So to show it one more time,
I guess I forgot I had this slide.
So as I move down,
you can see that more headers get wrapped.
And as I move back up,
the headers get unwrapped.
So that's how it works.
Okay.
So something interesting about this
is if you look at these headers,
you can almost think of the header
as talking to your equivalent
on the other side.
So what I mean by that is,
let's look at this header right here,
the one on the envelope.
It was written by the secretary on Alice's side,
and it's read by the secretary on Bob's side.
So it's almost like this header
is the two secretaries talking to each other,
in some sense.
This secretary said,
hey, give it to Bob.
And this secretary reads the message,
oh, it's for Bob.
And likewise,
if I look at this outermost header,
this is kind of like the mailman talking to each other.
So the first mailroom writes,
oh, it's for Bob's street address.
And then this one says,
oh, okay, I'm Bob's street address.
I'll receive this and cast it up.
So you can almost think of these headers
as a specific layer talking to its peers
at the other layer.
So in some sense,
all the layers are talking to each other
using the headers.
That's kind of cool.
And kind of a consequence of this is
everyone cares about the header at their layer,
but they ignore everything else.
So the mailman cares about street addresses.
They do not care about what's going on inside the buildings.
And likewise,
the secretary cares about the envelope.
The secretary does not care about the message inside.
And the CEO,
they only care about the message inside.
They don't care about the rest.
So everyone's working at their own layer.
That layer has a header.
And when you put something in that header,
you're basically talking to your peers at that same layer.
So that's kind of a nice consequence
of the way that we built this.
Okay.
Something else I want to call out
when we look at the packets getting passed up and down
is that there's actually different addressing schemes
being used at different layers.
And this is something we'll spend lots of time on.
But just to give you a quick preview,
there are different ways to address people.
So for example,
the secretaries think about people
and their names.
The secretary thinks,
oh, this is Alice.
This is Bob.
Secretary is thinking about people's names.
By contrast, the mailman,
mailman is not thinking about names.
The mailman is thinking in terms of addresses,
like 123 Alice Street,
or 456 Bob Street,
or 2551 Hearst Avenue.
So just like how in real life,
we address things differently,
people have names,
people have street addresses,
people have office numbers.
Well, in the internet,
there are also going to be lots of different ways
to address people
and different layers
have different ways of addressing people.
That's something we'll see.
Okay.
So here's the picture one more time.
But now I'm going to show it in terms of
the actual layers that we've been seeing.
So again,
the application comes up
with some message that they want to send.
There's nothing to do with the internet.
It's just a message.
And as we move down the stack,
we add a layer four header.
Layer four header passes it down.
Now there's the layer three header
passes it down.
Layer two header.
And now all the headers are wrapped around
and layer one converts this packet
to ones and zeros
and sends the ones and zeros
along a wire
or an optical fiber
or a radio wave or whatever.
So all the headers get wrapped around.
Layer one converts it to bits,
transmits it.
That's like the mail truck driving across town.
And then this fully encapsulated packet
with all the headers around it,
it's received on the other side on a wire.
And now we can start peeling off the layers
like an onion.
So the physical layer,
it gets the ones and zeros,
passes it up to the link layer.
The link layer unwraps its header,
passes it up to the internet layer.
The internet layer reads its header
to understand what to do,
unwraps it, passes it up to layer four.
Layer four reads its header,
learns what to do with it,
passes it up to layer seven,
and now layer seven gets the original message again.
Pretty much what you've already seen,
but showing it in terms of the actual internet layers
instead of post offices.
Okay.
And as mentioned before,
you can think of the headers
as a specific layer
talking to its peers
at that same layer.
So for example,
I rewind a little bit
and I look here.
When layer three added this header,
who's going to read this header on the other side?
The layer three person on the other side
is going to read this exact header.
So when you make a layer at header three,
on the other side,
it's their layer three implementation
that's reading that header.
And likewise,
when layer four added a header,
it's for the other side's layer four to read.
So on some sense,
on some level,
you can think of the protocols
as interacting with their peers
at the same layer,
which is kind of useful.
And these are all fancy acronyms
for protocols that we're going to see
throughout the class.
You don't have to know them now,
but maybe you recognize a few,
maybe you don't.
We'll talk about all of them later,
so stay tuned.
Okay, we're almost done.
So so far,
I've shown you how the packet travels
from point A to point B.
But as we mentioned earlier,
there's one last piece we have to put together
so that all the puzzle pieces fit together.
The last piece we need is that,
well, it's not the case
that Alice is directly connected to Bob.
So remember,
in the post office,
things can hop across multiple post offices
before they reach their destination.
And in the same way,
packets can travel across multiple hops,
multiple routers,
before they reach their destination.
So it's not the case that my packet
just directly goes to its destination,
like we saw in the example from before,
like the mail truck just drives straight
to Bob's building.
Could be the case
that we have to take the mail
to another post office,
and then they put it on a boat
and put it on this post,
send it to this post office,
and then they put it on a pigeon
and send it to this post office.
So it could be the case
that it has to hop across multiple post offices.
So we're actually now going to
do the exact same picture from before,
Alice sending mail to Bob,
but now we're going to add post offices
into the mix
to get the full picture
of what sending packets
with lots of headers looks like.
Okay, so here we go.
Alice is up here.
She's the CEO as always.
She sends a message,
gives it to the secretary.
Secretary writes down it's from Alice to Bob.
Pass it down to the mailman.
Mailman writes down Alice's street address
and Bob's street address.
Pass it down to the post office.
And here's the new thing
that we didn't have before.
This post office says
on post office number seven,
I'm not directly connected
to post office number nine.
So I can't just send this packet directly to nine.
I don't have a mailman
who's going to go to post office nine.
My carrier pigeons
are not trained to go to post office nine.
So instead, I'm going to say,
well, on post office seven,
I can't get this directly to nine.
But you know what I can do?
I can get it to post office two.
Post office two is not the final destination,
but it's closer.
So I got it closer.
So we are now adding
this extra layer of header
that says this is not going to reach
its final destination right away,
but I'll get it closer.
So post office seven,
a post office number seven,
post a letter in an even bigger box
or like on a truck or something.
And that bigger box
is destined for post office number two.
So it's still wrapped in a bunch of layers.
We just wrapped it around one extra layer
that we weren't showing earlier.
Now this goes to post office two.
But what does post office two do?
Well, remember this outer layer
is for the post offices to talk to each other.
So we unwrap that layer,
exposing the headers inside,
and the post office looks at this and says,
I'm not four, five, six Bob Street.
It's not for me.
But this needs to reach four, five, six Bob Street.
How does it get there?
I need to forward this packet
to get it closer to four, five, six Bob Street.
So I can't reach that address,
but you know who can?
Post office number five.
That's my next neighbor who gets closer.
So I'm going to wrap another header around
that says I'm post office two.
I'm sending this over to my buddy,
post office number five.
They're probably closer.
So I did my job.
I got this packet closer to its destination.
And we send this on a boat or something
and it reaches post office number five.
Post office number five unwraps the outer header
like it always does.
This is the header that post offices use.
So I unwrap the post office header.
I expose the inner headers.
And I say, you know what?
This is not for me either.
I'm not four, five, six Bob Street.
But you know who is?
Post office nine is they're connected to Bob.
So I'm going to wrap this in another header,
send it over to post office number nine
and post office number nine receives the packet,
unwraps it and finally says,
me, this is me.
I am connected to four, five, six Bob Street.
Like I'm in that town.
So I'm going to go ahead and send this over
to four, five, six Bob Street.
So four, five, six Bob Street receives this packet
and the rest is as we've seen before.
The mailroom opens up this box
and unwraps this header, revealing the envelope,
give the envelope to the secretary.
Secretary gives the envelope to the CEO.
And we are finally done.
That was a lot.
But that's kind of what it looks like in real life.
So instead of the mailrooms directly connected
to each other, which is generally not true,
this packet traveled across multiple post offices
and the outermost layer corresponding
to the lowest layer of abstraction, the post offices,
they would send the packet to their next hop
to get closer and closer to the destination.
So that's the postal version of what we've just seen.
But I introduced multiple post offices.
Okay, great.
So just to show it to you one more time,
this is the path that the packet took.
Intermediate post offices repeatedly removed
and added the outer header.
So everyone would take it off, add a new one,
take it off, add a new one.
But this inner stuff always remained the same.
It was always the same original packet,
a destined for its destination.
So that's the postal analogy,
but with post offices introduced.
Okay, so to show it to you one more time,
these are the headers and we can think about
what they're doing.
The outermost header, it thinks in terms of post offices.
It says who is the next intermediate post office
to get this packet closer to its destination?
Post office five is probably not the final destination,
but it's closer.
I just want to get it closer.
That's all I care about.
And layer three,
this is where we're putting the actual destination.
This is the original source of the packet.
This is the final destination of the packet
in terms of street addresses.
So up here, two and five could be intermediate post offices,
but this is always going to be the original source
and the final destination.
And then inside here, A and B,
those were specific people inside the building.
So once I reach Bob Street,
lots of people are working in Bob Street.
Bob is working there, someone else is working there.
So all of those people could be at four, five, six Bob Street.
So I have to uniquely identify,
it's not just for anyone in four or five, six Bob Street,
it's for B specifically, it's for that person.
And it's from A,
not just anyone in one, two, three Alice Street,
but A, that's the person who sent it.
So the very lowest layer,
we have the post offices,
then we have the actual destination and source
in terms of street addresses.
And at the innermost layer,
which is the highest layer,
so something I haven't really called out yet,
the inner layers are higher
because of the way we wrap them.
So this innermost layer, highest layer of abstraction,
we think about people inside the building.
Alice is the person inside the building,
Bob is the person inside the building,
but it could have been other people inside the building.
Maybe there's another person in the Bob building.
So also the CEO could have gone to them as well.
So that's why we need multiple addressing schemes
working at different layers of abstraction.
Okay, thoughts before I keep going?
Okay, almost done.
So what we actually just saw also tells us
what layers each machine has to understand.
So let's think about the end hosts.
What do the end hosts have to think about?
Turns out the end hosts have to think about everything
because the end host has to think about the original packet
and then the end host has to wrap it
all the way down to layer one,
where it becomes ones and zeros and is sent on the wire.
So if you're the end host, like you're Alice or you're Bob,
your computer has to understand all seven layers.
You start at layer seven with the message
and you wrap headers around and around and around
all the way until you get that nested packet
that can get sent along the wire.
And likewise, at the very end,
when you reach the destination,
they also have to take the packet, unwrap, unwrap, unwrap, unwrap,
before they can get the final packet
with none of the headers attached.
So basically the punchline is,
you'll notice that the end hosts had to understand
all of the layers of abstraction.
So they have to have code for all five layers.
By contrast, think about the routers.
Did the routers ever like open the envelope
to look at the message inside?
No, not really.
Did they have to understand what was on the envelope
and understand who Alice and Bob were?
No, not really.
What did the routers have to do?
They had to unwrap their outermost header,
look inside to see who the final destination is,
and then wrap a header to send it to the next top.
That's it.
So in other words, the routers only care about layers
one, two, and three.
They start at one because everyone starts at one
with all the packet headers sent along the wire.
They unwrap their layer, which is layer two,
exposing the layer three destination.
That's the final destination.
I read that, and I think, I can't get to four, five, six,
Bob Street, but you know who can?
It's my buddy next door.
So then I'll wrap another link layer header
and then send it to my hub next door.
So that's something we'll see in just a bit.
Basically, the punchline is end hosts have to understand
all the layers, whereas routers only have to make their way
up to layer three, and they don't really care about
what's inside beyond that.
So from their perspective, you get to layer three.
Everything beyond that is just payload gibberish.
I don't care what the message is.
That's for the end host to decide.
So what that means is routers don't care about reliability.
They don't care about the application data.
They just care about these bottom three layers.
Okay.
Here's a picture of what I just talked about.
So I started the very top message.
What do I do?
I wrap it in layer four.
I wrap it in layer three, layer two.
Then I convert it to bits and I send it across the wire.
Now I get to the router.
And just like we talked about, the router doesn't care that this says potato.
The router is never going to read that.
From the router's perspective, this could be any word or any message.
It doesn't matter.
But the router does care about unwrapping this outermost header.
So I receive the bits.
I parse them to understand what they mean.
I unwrap this layer two header, revealing the layer three header inside,
which remember that tells me where the final destination is.
And then I wrap another layer two header.
I wrap another layer one header or, you know, convert it to ones and zeros.
Then I send it across over here and this router does the same thing.
Unwrapped layers one and two.
I read layer three to understand where this packet is going.
And then I pass this back down to layer two, add a new header,
pass it on to layer one, add a new header and send it over.
Maybe another way of putting that is once I get here to layer three,
all this stuff inside blue and purple is complete payload gibberish.
I don't care what it is.
It's just a bunch of ones and zeros.
I don't know how to read them.
I don't care what they say.
I just care about this layer three header to figure out where the packet is going next.
I wrap a new layer two header to my next top and then I send the bits across the wire.
And once I reach the end, the end host does care about potato.
The end host is the one trying to receive this message.
So the end host will pass the packet all the way back up unwrapped unwrapped unwrapped.
And I get the original message back.
So once I add routers into the picture, this is what it looks like.
End host understand all seven layers.
Routers only understand the first three.
Okay.
Sounds good.
Here's a cartoon arrow showing you the path that the packets took.
I went down the stack here and then at every router,
it went up the stack unwrapped to see where the final destination is.
And then go back down, wrap some more headers to tell me where the packet is going next.
Hop over here, go up, go down, up over here,
travel all the way up the stack to reach the final destination.
So this kind of pattern is what packets do as they travel through the internet.
Packets, headers get unwrapped and wrapped over and over again.
But these higher layer headers always stay the same.
Okay.
So as mentioned earlier, you saw this before with post offices,
but now I'm going to show it to you in computer form.
So the layer two headers, what addresses are they thinking about?
They're thinking in terms of the intermediate routers.
I'm router two.
The next hop is router number five is router five, the final destination.
Probably not, but router five will get this packet closer to where it needs to go.
And I'm router two.
So these are intermediate routers that forward the packet hop by hop as they approach the final destination.
Layer three, this is actually the real final destination.
Alice's computer, Bob's computer.
These are the actual final destinations and they never change.
As the packet travels across the network, it's always from Alice, it's always to Bob.
This outer one is where the intermediate hops change.
And then finally, once it reaches Alice's computer and you unwrap it,
you get specific applications on her computer.
So it could be that Alice's Firefox application is talking to Bob's Google Chrome application,
or it could be the case that, you know, the zoom application on my computer is talking to the zoom application on your computer.
So once we get to a specific computer, we can identify applications on the computer,
just like how once we reach a building, we can identify people inside the building by their room number or by their name.
And then at the very inside, we have the original message.
So that's kind of what it looks like.
Question.
Yeah, that's a great question.
The question was, can you access a header if the outer headers have not been unwrapped yet?
Or is it the case that you have to wait for the outer ones to be unwrapped before you can access the header?
So remember, this is all just ones and zeros.
When I actually look at this packet on the wire, or if I look at it in my computer, it's just a pile of ones and zeros.
So if you want to, you can certainly skip to the end and like look at potato.
So if this is encoded in ones and zeros, I can certainly skip to the end and look at the ones and zeros.
But in real life, what most commonly happens is that the protocols only look at the headers and then for them.
And the way that we wrap and unwrap ensures that that's true.
That's a great question though.
Any other ones?
Okay.
So as mentioned one more time, just to really hammer it home, routers don't care about layers four and seven.
So from the router's perspective, they're going to read this.
They're going to read this stuff in green and all the stuff in blue and purple.
Who cares?
It's bunch of ones and zeros.
I have no idea what it means.
So from their perspective, this is just payload garbage.
So you can almost think of it as this is the header.
All of this stuff is the payload, including this extra header that I just don't know how to parse.
So I'm going to unwrap the layer two header.
I'm going to read this layer three header to say, oh, it's going to Bob.
That's the final destination.
And I'll add a new layer two header that brings this closer to its destination.
So router two, five and nine, those are not Alice or Bob.
They're intermediate routers, but I can receive a packet, unwrap the outermost header.
Cheek inside and say, okay, it's for Bob.
Add a new header that says router nine will get this closer to Bob.
And then all this stuff beyond layer three, there's four and seven.
I don't care.
I can't even read them.
It's all great.
Technically, you're right.
It's ones and zeros.
I can read it if I wanted to.
And near the end of the class, we'll break some of these rules.
But for now, complete garbage.
I don't care what it says.
Okay.
I'm almost done.
So remember one thing we saw earlier, which is that when packets get sent
across the internet, something great about layers of abstraction is that packets
can actually be sent using different link technology as they hop across links.
So remember the packet could travel along a wire across the sea and they can go
across a wireless link and then go across an optical link or whatever.
Well, turns out the exact same thing could happen here in this picture.
So although I didn't really call it out here, it could be the case that this header
and this header are for different level layer two interfaces or protocols.
So for example, this layer two header could be for wireless.
This kind of information beyond the front and the two that wireless routers understand.
And then this header could be for things that only wired hosts understand for
electrical cables.
So it could be the case that this link is wired.
This link is optical.
This link is wireless.
That's totally fine.
The internet works on layers and so we can support this.
And what that means that this router is that this router is going to see a wired
layer two header because it gets the packet on a wire, unwraps the layer two
header that has all this information about wires.
And then because the next link happens to be optical, it's going to add a new header
that has all sorts of optical information, which we're not even going to talk about.
But basically the idea is that the header you unwrap and the header you wrap
don't necessarily have to be the same at layer two.
And that's what enables us to use different link layer technologies.
I can unwrap a wired header and then wrap an optical header with different information
using a different protocol, send it across the optical link.
This router unwraps the optical link and says, you know what?
The next hop is wireless.
I'm going to add a wireless header and then send this over a wireless channel.
That's totally fine.
But one thing I will notice that if you do this, this router has to speak two languages.
It has to understand what wired headers look like to unwrap the wired header.
And it also has to understand optical headers so that it can add its own optical header.
So if it is the case that you're connected to two different technologies, like my computer
is connected using a wire and it's also broadcasting radio waves,
then my computer has to speak two languages.
It has to know how to read wired layer two headers and also optical layer two headers.
And same thing with this router.
It has to understand optical headers and wireless headers.
So basically you can think of it as this router speaks two languages.
And that's what enables us to use different links across the life of this packet
as they get sent across the internet.
Okay.
So believe it or not, I didn't actually time this lecture.
So I'm kind of amazed that it turned out as good as it did is two minutes before the lecture ends.
So to quickly summarize today, I just want to give you a heads up because I saw a lot of questions on the zoom as well.
Today is an overview.
We're going to spend basically this entire semester breaking down lots of the things that we saw today.
So totally natural if you have more questions, we can take them.
And there's going to be lots of lectures covering the things that we talked about today in more detail.
But I just wanted to give you a 10,000 foot high level view of what the internet looks like.
So to summarize the big ideas of today, we built the internet using layers of abstraction.
And these are the five layers that we decided on.
We started with bits moving across space.
We use them to link up a local network.
We use that to link up the entire internet in the network of networks topology that we talked about.
Then we added transport to guarantee reliability because the internet was best effort.
And then finally, users can build whatever applications they want.
As packets move down the stack, we add headers and we nest them.
And as packets move up the stack, we unwrap the headers.
And that created this little funny shape that we saw from earlier.
Also, we saw that hosts have to understand layers one through seven top to bottom because they want to parse the end packet.
Whereas routers only have to understand layers one through three.
And we saw that at layer two.
Your destination is the next intermediate router.
It says go to router five.
They're not the destination, but they're going to get you closer.
Layer three is always the end host and the original sender.
And layer four identify specific applications on the end host.
Think of it like specific people in the building.
Okay.
So with that, that's it for today and we'll see you next week.
And if you have questions, we can take them up front.